嗯。
誒一啲團體嚟，唔該曬。
佢先個仔都幾懶。
平靚過，平靚過，平靚過。
係。
O.K.
我不如講佢，佢團體名仲好講。
講名，講名啦。
大啲，大啲。
啊，鋪緊嘛，大你談得啦，你大你想啲數字，數數想啲康康辦出嚟。
呢啲重啲啦，呢個講名名辛苦。
依個啱唔啱啊？
唔該曬。
今日咧就係我哋呢個，我哋今日嘅議題咧就誒講改善難民、候認升升整者及尋求庇護者喺香港生活狀況。噉我哋咧就今日就總共有保安局首席助理秘書長就胡德英先生，同社會福利處誒處長麥周淑霞女士，同埋社會。
福利處助理處長同馮文仲先生歡迎大家。我亦都希望你哋先係啦，簡單介紹下啊嘛，唔該。
主席，我好簡單講兩句咧，就誒相關議題嘅誒一啲誒政策考慮嗰個細節安排，同埋誒近年最新嘅發展咧。其實我哋喺剛剛誒提出嘅文件咧都羅列咗出嚟嘅。噉我哋今日好高興有機會咧，可以係同議員同埋不同關注團體。
係咧，係。
團體我哋唔使佢入嘅，我入嘅。
好啊！噉我哋好高興今日有機會可以作一個即係聽到團體嘅意見。噉我諗我哋聽完曬意見之後咧，我同社署嘅同事咧再一拼去即係同大家討論同埋會談嚇。
我亦都想誒，等團體入嚟嘅時候咧，同同事講。今日咧，我哋有兩個唔同嘅題目，就兩個組合嘅。
即係福利同我哋，即係呢呢個項目咧，本來就請請咗誒保安，但係保安佢話佢今日嚟啦。噉我哋下一part就講錄讀者嘅，就同民政主席咧就由民政做主席。咁所以變咗我哋時間比較緊張啲，即係話我哋而家由呢個三點鐘到誒四點半。
而且要喺內完咗，就跟住到下一拍，好嘛？唔該曬。
噉啊！我哋團體入緊嚟哦。
新到嚟一個。
我哋哋。
好。
你講。
國際咩？
O.K.
係係係。
做正。
嘅中文就係咩？
國際社。
第二個屬於咩？就香港語。
民族復健復健中心應該係咩？
呢個中文我哋都冇。
係真係有難處啫。
Okay.
好。
thank you。
誒，我哋。
可以，係可以可以講。
我仲話住。
誒，我或者誒同所嚟嘅團體啦。
誒，大家就首先帶起個好似雨風嗰個物體。
iPhone。
我哋有唔同嘅誒收聽嘅，如果係用英語嘅咧。
就係呢個二號，如果係用現場咧，就零號；粵語咧，就一號。
睇下大家係啦，如果唔熟嘅揾我哋啲工作人員幫手啊！
我哋揾啲同事幫幫手嘛。
係啦。
都似。
你第一次。
呢個。
OK。
係啊！啲。
誒，如果答案冇問題咧，跟住我哋就係，如果有問題請舉手，唔熟嘅就係啦。
如果冇問題咧，就係我誒想同大家講講，我哋咧任何團體嚟到呢度咧，或者個人咧，就係誒。
佢哋喺會議上發現唔受到立法會嘅權力及特權條例第三百八十二條所定嘅保障及豁免嘅，同時各位代表提交意見書，同樣唔喺呢個條例保障豁免嘅範圍內。
好啦。
我哋誒政府就係主要嚟聽意見係嘛？O K好，噉我而家我首先請團體先，就每個團體咧係三分鐘。
我哋首先請第一位咧，first。
呢個International Social Service Hong Kong Branch。
please。
佢哋仲未掂。
係，我就嚟講，唔好意思啊。第一個未冇嚟到，第三。
第三。
誒第三位，第一、第二位都未到，第三位係誒工黨嘅副秘書長郭永健先生。係啊，大家好。咁工黨咧就住難民同埋僑營申請者嘅生活狀況係有以下嘅意見嘅。咁而家香港咧有四千七百名難民啦。咁咧，但係佢哋即係啊，滯留喺香港期間。
得到嘅對待咧並不人道嘅，以美國有線新聞網、有線電視新聞網咧係甚至用呢個羞恥同埋猶如被囚禁咧嚟形容難民喺香港嘅生活。工黨咧認為香港係作為經濟發達地區同埋國際社會嘅一份子咧，係有能力同埋有責任咧係畀難。
難民佢哋有一個最基本嘅保障。另外咧，工黨都認為咧應該係加快審核佢哋難民身份，等佢哋咧滯留咧都係誒，即係可以盡快到達收容國，或者咧係遣返去原居地。
而家難民抵港之後咧，首先會向聯合國難民專員公署申請難民身份啦，等待確認嗰個時間咧係長達三年。等到確認之後咧，就要去到即係收人國收容國嗰度咧去申請。咁呢個過程咧又要幾年啦。咁身份咧未能得到確認，又唔想被遣返咧，又可以即係去到。
到特區政府咧，係啊，即係申請嗰個學型申請，而呢個過程咧又係要三年，三年又三年。佢哋嘅生活咧係充滿住等待。就喺呢個長達六年嘅等待過程之中，難民咧冇得喺即係香港嗰度工作啦，亦冇辦法讀書。即使咧話去慈善團體嗰度做義工，都係不被允許嘅。
由於佢哋無法工作，所以咧只有依靠呢個國際社會服務社去申請基本嘅援助嚟維持佢哋基本嘅生活。佢哋每十日就得到一袋嘅食物，咁入邊咧係有啲簡單嘅，即係蔬果啊、雞蛋啊、麵包噉樣。而住所嘅租金咧係由國際社畀，但係咧個租金最多咧係得個一千二。
百蚊，加上咧，即係國際勢係唔會提供呢個租金嘅上期或者按金，好少業主咧願意係租出呢啲單位畀難民。以噉嘅租金水平同埋噉樣誒嘅條件咧，實在好難喺香港揾到一個基本嘅居所。
就以喺啊，即係平斜租住嘅難民為例啦。佢哋平斜嘅居所咧，好多都係由豬欄改建而成，條件咧係十分之簡陋嘅。而咧佢哋嘅廁所同埋佢哋嘅即係廚房咧係擺埋一齊，衞生情況非常惡劣。喺咁惡劣嘅環境之下咧，即使咧佢哋生病咧。
都要咧先向呢個國際社係申請呢個醫藥費同埋交通費，要等到批准之後咧，先可以去睇病。
而家咧，政府咧係資助咗兩億畀香港國際社會服務社啦，但係成效咧係充滿疑問。已經有傳媒報道過咧，即係佢哋嘅難民嘅租住合約咧，有唔少人咧係報住一啲唔存在嘅地址，但係實際上咧係被安排住喺個啊豬籠寮屋嗰度。咁咧有團體甚至係質疑呢個做。
做法係自在掩飾、不人道對待真相。總括而言咧，工黨認為香港對於難民咧係應該提供一個人道嘅援助，政府應該全盤檢討現時支援難民喺食物、醫療、教育、交通上嘅支援，應該提供資助畀非政府機構為難民咧舉辦一啲唔同嘅活動，同埋。
係等佢哋咧可以參與義務工作，同時應該係縮短咧佢哋嗰個審核嘅啊時間嘅。O.K.呢個時間都夠啦。跟住咧，我哋第一個團體第一個咧就係呢個係International Social Service Hong Kong關注，唔該。
謝謝，主席。
International Social Service Hong Kong Branch has been serving the local community and migrants and refugees in Hong Kong since fifty-five years ago, and we have such an extensive background in dealing with its welfare assistance. Since two thousand and six, ISS Hong Kong has been designated by the government through a tender process.
to provide this assistance project.
我咪just highlight the guidelines by which we operate as a contracted agency of the government.
一， assistance is humanitarian and it's a tied-over grant. This is a government statement and aimed at preventing the service clients from destitution. It is not equivalent to welfare assistance.
All service clients of ISS are referred by social welfare department to us. We are not accepting any walk-in clients because they have to be initially assessed by social welfare department, and they have to be looked at in terms of sense of urgency and the kind of assistance that they would require.
The referrals by which social welfare department IFSCs are acted upon by ISS is again dependent on sense of urgency.
The casework approach that's being used is on the premise that one social worker or caseworker is appointed for every client. The current ratio is one social worker has 130 clients, which is almost double the amount of the ratio with the local integrated family service centres.
The assistance in kind does not come as a package. There is an eligibility criteria for every assistance. So if somebody comes and even if the package consists of accommodation, food, clothing, toiletries, transportation, it doesn't come automatic. What has to happen is there's a
system for an interview process with every client, and every client is assessed on an eligibility criteria with requirements defined by social welfare department on when each client can be accepted or not, and when discretionary decisions are made. This is very clear.
主要係喺ISS和SWD合約。
一合同協議 between ISS and the client is simply stating that the client is found to be eligible for that specific assistance in the agreement for a period of one month.
this monthly agreement is reviewed when the clients show up for a renewal of the agreement, so it's always on a monthly basis and not a long-term basis at all. This is why it's considered as a tied-over grant.
There is no distinction as to where you live in Hong Kong. You can be in Hong Kong Island, Kowloon or new territories. The same types of assistance can be offered.
The differences in the levels of assistance and the types of assistance depends on the result of actually the interview process.
我認為細節的援助是列出的。ISS有什麼要説？
是 simply that all of this, all of the manner modalities by which this assistance is delivered, is part of an agreement in a tender contract between social welfare department and ISS Hong Kong. ISS cannot act on its own or create policies on its own or even do a budget.
on its own, everything is granted and decided upon by the social welfare department and the government. Now we are pleased.
當我們來到這個項目在2006年，主要的成就就是。
The refugees, asylum seekers and torture claimants are no longer living in detention centres and refugee camps, which is a primary thing that ISS wants to consider.
Community living is is something that we want to actually make sure continues to happen. Now, whether the assistance is not enough or enough, sorry, the ISS just wants to say that we are open for any suggestions and open for whatever changes would be discussed.
Thank you, thank you, thank you.
Now we would like to invite the executive director of the Hong Kong Refugee Advice Centre, Miss.
Thank you. My name's Elita Miller. I'm the executive director of the Hong Kong Refugee Advice Centre, or HKRAC. HKRAC is a non-governmental organisation which provides free legal assistance to asylum seekers in Hong Kong. In our six years of operation, we've assisted more than 1,500 people.
for far too long, the Hong Kong government has treated protection claimants as temporary recipients of humanitarian assistance, a measure intended to prevent destitution.
然而，香港有國際法律義務對所有人民，無論其移民身分，要尊重、保護和實現他們的社會經濟權利，包括享有足夠的生活水準。這個義務超越了防止貧窮。
The reality is that right now, many protection claimants are suffering destitution in Hong Kong while waiting for their claims to be determined. Right now, Hong Kong is not fulfilling its international legal obligations.
The current policy is bad for protection claimants and bad for Hong Kong. With no right to work, protection claimants are unable to provide for themselves and their families, to use their time productively or to contribute to our society.
保護申請者必須能住得有安全，和有尊嚴。
他們必須either被頒發權力去工作，去支持 themselves，或給予足夠的協助，去實現足夠的標準生活。現時，他們沒有。
civil society organisations have been filling the gap and struggling to protect claimants from abject poverty, but we cannot continue to do so indefinitely. The Hong Kong government must step up and meet its responsibilities to claimants.
The current assistance package must be re-evaluated. Policy reform must move from providing assistance and preventing destitution towards respecting rights, ensuring security and dignity, and promoting self-reliance.
我們 urge the government to establish fair, transparent and accountable assistance criteria. We petition the government to conduct a comprehensive review of current assistance, including participation of protection claimants themselves and civil society organisations.
香港是個富庶城市，有國際聲譽，以人權和法治為主。但現時香港正在浪費資源，透過一個不夠有效率和不夠有效的系統，而失去臉面。
個別個基本權利係被Denied，，and people are suffering.
ensuring protection claimants' rights will fulfil Hong Kong's human rights obligations, resurrect Hong Kong's reputation as a world city and avoid Hong Kong being shamed on the international stage. Let's act now to remedy an unfair and inefficient system. We encourage the government to create a mechanism to collaborate with civil
社會， and to continue this dialogue. By working together, we can move towards a sustainable solution firmly grounded in human rights. Thank you.
跟住第。
我會像要請Mr. Tarik講話，Mr. Tarik，請。
Thank you very much and good afternoon, officers. I appreciate some policies from the ISS department and what I was heard earlier. Like we are not in detention centres anymore, but the problem is when we were out and we went to out to find rooms for ourselves.
We were not given rooms and whenever we went to any agency to find room, they were asking us the deposit. Do you have the deposit? And well, of course not. Then they were not willing to help us. Recently, I was kicked out from my landlord last month.
30th of June and
Well，我 had no place to live， so that night I slept in a stadium.
and then very next day some of my friends they called me for to live with them for a short while, and I was agreed. I find a room. I found a room like there were four people already living. It's very small and I could not even, you know, if I'm lying down I cannot turn on my other side. It was that small. So I started look.
looking for places. Whenever I went to the agency, they were asking me for the same thing. Do you have the deposit? And I said I don't have. And then they were asking me what job do you have? And I said I'm ISS client. And when I said ISS, they said we don't accept ISS. And well, some of the agencies they really don't.
don't want to hear the name of ISS and at one of the agencies I asked them why what is the reason and they said we are not getting the payment like if you three people are living together.
The ISS will pay.
amount 1,200 Hong Kong dollar， but not at the fixed date。
different dates you will be you will your your monthly rent will be transferred like eighth of the month and then some of them will be tenth or earlier or later so we don't accept it and.
The other thing is the food collection. They are asking us to collect food six times, and I don't see anything. Why six times do we have to collect the food?
and。
Well， the main problem is。
We don't have the deposit, and I gathered the deposit from some of my friends, and they ask me, you have to write something. We need your signature that you are going to pay us back that deposit. That was twelve thousand five hundred Hong Kong dollars, and I'm struggling. How can I pay them back?
and without deposit, I cannot find any any place to live.
Okay, thank you. Thank you.
我會嚟，like to invite Mrs. Pereira to speak. Mrs. Pereira, I would I would like to thanks Vision First Group for me chance to talking about my.
stories and good afternoon sir. even my house rent was six thousand seven hundred, but ISS paying for me six thousand.
for every month. So I ask I S S. How can I find the money? Then they tell me to go and find the money somewhere else. And even the Vishnu's Christian Action and somewhere else. How can I go and find somewhere else?
所以，even the food is not enough food. I have three children. My elder son is 23 years, and second son 16.
Third son, fifteen years. Even my husband and me, we are five of them in the family. So not enough food. Even every day, every same things. I cannot choose even the food.
所以我 ask，我 want to choose something else，但係佢哋 say no。  whatever we are providing， you have to take， no choice。
所以，even the my children going to school， they have to cut hair。
every month， so where is the money？
even the bus fare transportation， they are not paying even properly。 if I go see my lawyer， they giving half rate of the bus fare。 so no anything do properly。 so ISS never do anything properly。 I can say that。
Thank you very much.
Yes, we would like to invite Mr. Bissen to speak. Good, I have some photos I'm going to share with you. So destitute claimants forced into slums.
所以，基本上，我們的聲明是，高等法院烏茲曼巴特判決是Binding on the government to offer support，which is considered sufficient to prevent a person from becoming destitute.
嗯。
ISS pays fourteen hundred dollars for two claimants living under this tree.
一個 abandon pig farm is subdivided into tiny rooms. Seven different addresses.
destitute claimants cannot move out without deposit money.
claimants recover usable items from rubbish dumps.
this is the bathroom in the converted pig farm, not without hot water in the winter.
電電器工和meter是 illegal，Ices never pays electricity in the area of Pincher to claimants.
claimants are refunded gas every five to six months in Kowloon, people get it every two to three months。
等等，誒。
呢個。This room has a toilet next to the bed. I have inspected this room for five years.
廁所 fitted unhygienically in cooking areas, rats are known to climb out of them.
這 squat toilet flushes into an infested open drain.
另一個compound is makes use of an abandoned home where twelve claimants live with six different addresses.
這間廚房是用一個生鏽的辦公桌做來的。
The shower is a wooden shack, waterproof with bags.
by inspecting this compound over five years, ISS obviously approved it.
八名claimants have been living here for five years without toilets.
ISS claims local live in similar conditions. You can compare the shack in front with the villa behind.
一 makeshift kitchen with plastic sheets for ceiling.
The shower is fitted in an alleyway between two buildings.
Despite paying 120 rent a month, these claimants walk day and night 300 metres to a public toilet. That's 1,200 sorry a month. These claimants walk to the public toilets every.
This compound is interesting. These three claimants have been ICS clients for five years, yet their homes have never been inspected.
I assess claims case by case assessment for its needs, for clients' needs. Yet.
They haven't visited this this compound. This this shack is obviously very dangerous and unlivable.
just going fast because run out of time. So a shower and toilet fitted in a passageway. This is a an apartment. This is a block shown in one of the addresses of an ISS contract, and the tenants don't know about ISS here. I'll explain. So international social service stated.
Can I continue, please? Yeah, international social service said that all the shortfalls in assistance to claimants are not ISS fault.
Ms. Panaris said that ICES hands are tied. ICES position is that the security bureau is to blame for withholding necessary funding to claimants.
社會福利部門是 accountable for working alongside ISS in an oversight capacity. SWD and ISS kept the amount of assistance unchanged with inflation. With inflation, this amounts to failing to meet claimants' most basic needs.
SWNIS的行為是誣衊和不當。
Security Bureau重複地 stated in High Court that claimants' needs are fully met, and there is no need to review this policy.
Security Bureau is in breach of Usmanbat case and its fiduciary duties towards claimants. Security Bureau has full knowledge of what is happening, skyrocketing inflation, and I assess maintaining fixed and unchanged rental payments since 2010.
EDB、Hospital Authority、Immigration， combine to ensure claimants are attacked by the government on all fronts.
我 just okay. I just draw my conclusion. Government has allowed departments to continue welfare assistance under the false assumptions that claimants' basic material financial needs are met. This amounts to actual knowledge and willful blindness. My con our conclusion is that Hong Kong government has substantially failed to fulfil its international and.
constitutional obligations towards claimants. The PowerPoint is on our website. Thank you.
Now we would like to invite Mr. Hoeder to speak.
Thank you for Bishan first, and thank you Legislative Counsellor. So I would like to say, sir, about our problem, the ISIS. ISIS basically they are paying to room rent a thousand two hundred dollars, but it's not sufficient. In Hong Kong, cannot find the room rent like the thousand two hundred dollars. Without
deposit， we find the room is very difficult。
因為我們係 suffering for them every month need to go for contact and also for three times port collection, one time for go to the immigration signature. So always we are busy, but sometimes we don't have the any enough money to for transportation. So if like this suffering, how long we will we will?
do that. So need to be for us make the one good solution. The ISIS contact every month one time or long time contact. Every month we go to the ISIS is very difficult in setting. Then go for three times food collision and food is very lower class food. It's this one kind.
種 rice， this is the basmati rice。 actually， this is not basmati rice， and this that kind of rice we are eating， actually not good for our health。
所以 many people starvation for this food and the ISS signature and also the some problem is the medical treatment medical treatment is the if emergency they will do our treatment but if need the normally any kinds of operation as example.
我有心臟病，我係心臟病患者。上個月我到Queen Elizabeth Cardiac Department，佢哋畀我做手術日期。但係醫院唔畀我做手術，因為我冇錢。如果我有兩萬蚊，我就可以做手術。
So, we are really for the field the suffer in Hong Kong. Some problems facing is we cannot capacity to manage that. So sometimes we need the help from friends, but this not also enough. So I have request to
the legislative council for do the any permanent things for us. Thank you for give me the good chance and talking.
好，thank you。
我會嚟到 invite 市 Mr. Bashiru to speak。
Thank you very much for giving me this opporitity.
Yeah, I'm going to talk about.
some of the problem that facing us, but it is not seen. It's invisible.
and then，sometimes our appearance should not be the judgement of who we are。
yes。
The system has made some of us to be liars before our landlords.
because。
This is the only way we can secure our rooms.
When he ask you, when are you paying your rent? You only say my boss will give me money, whereas you are not working.
所以它創造某種 kind of。
tension，whenever the moon is coming to an end。
how to get this money to pay is a problem.
And then I have been a liar before my landlord for about three years now.
我 always try to change.
my statement.
所以我 ended up hanging back， wandering around everywhere。
for him to see that I'm working, whereas I'm not.
所以呢啲係一種啲情況，係。
We are facing.
And I'm one of the oldest people as far as this ISS is concerned. We were the first people to start this ISS since 2006.
and have been in this situation until now, and there's no any change.
Even though the boss of ISS has explained his side of the story.
we can not also just stand here and listen, but we we are also talking about our side, the way we are feeling.
因為，這係關於我們 life。
And we are people who are capable. We'll be able to exhibit what we have in case we have opportunity.
我喺度八個好年。
doing nothing.
我beginning to understand that I'm becoming useless.
despite the the skills that I can exhibit.
despite what I can produce as something that I think will be helpful to somebody.
We have been here for so many years now.
如果我們被 prevented from working,
what about keeping us busy?
doing something that we can keep it, so that we can use it for the rest of our lives.
Our time is getting over.
八 years doing nothing.
and we cannot be here just because we came here for happiness. no.
我係個老師。
我用嚟收 salary。
If it is about money,
consider the number of years I've spent here, I have not gained anything.
This should be.
and advise for me to go back if there is no problem.
所以。
我 just want to conclude that.
Whilst we are making arrangement to see how our condition will be changed.
Certain things must be considered regarding people who be willing to have some short courses.
要活著。
We cannot continue like this forever.
even if we should find ourselves in another location.
你有 hope。
now I want to tell you.
If now you ask a salency case to vote.
food。
and hope。
many people會choose hope。
Thank you very much.
哦，Thank you, Miss.
我哋想請Mrs. Dorothy講。
Thank you very much, ladies and gentlemen. We are really privileged to sit here before you and.
Put forward our problem. We are really honoured to be here. Thank you very much. I have four points to talk about.
The major point is the housing issue. The housing issue is a total nightmare in our community.
truly there is no room that rents out for 1,200 as we speak, except for a few places that are not supposed to be lived in by people, i.e. the pigsties, the owners converted into shelters and charge them as they wish.
If you are lucky to get a room and can't be paid up by ISS, the best solution is to cram yourselves into small rooms that are suitably for one person or two.
and as if that is not enough, landlords raise their rents whenever they feel like.
many of these dingy rooms have their rents raised every six months. With a complimentary, you can pack out if you can't pay.
as you know, we don't have any income to pay up the balance. we depend entirely on the government and the handouts from Good Samaritans.
點數二。
food， all we can say is that food is not enough。
我會給一個例子。
If you give me five kilograms of rice, a piece of chicken, a few grams of meat, five ripe bananas,
and maybe three tomatoes. I have to ration this food for ten good days.
believe me， is not enough。
worst of all， this same food is supposed to be divided into a portion of five day ratio。
by beginning of August, I'm not so sure whether we shall be receiving one banana, one orange, quarter a chicken. We don't know why such a small portion again is to be divided into two. Well, ISS knows why it is doing that. Still, it can't patch up the deficit.
We as
refugees or we who people who receive these services, we still oppose the collection of food for six times a month.
點數三，醫療，我們真係 appreciatе 」，醫療 waiver 」，由，提供由 ISS。
但當它來到見專家。
We are locked out. They say we don't qualify. If you need to see a specialist, you should pay. I myself, I walked into a hospital for a gynaecological problem.
我 had a waiver. They closed me out. They said I have to pay three thousand if I need to see a doctor. I really felt it was not fair on my side.
lastly，education for our children in our community we have all children of all ages these children need to go to school but most of the time the process to enrol them is made very hard for us to have a breakthrough it is so complicated in every angle you turn to worst worst of all
May I conclude, please? Just conclusion. Worst of all, all we are requesting is enough subsistence as we wait, because without enough subsistence, there's nothing much we can say about it. Thank you very much.
好，thank you，next。
誒，我想同各位朋友講，今日院我哋嘅會好緊張，所以每個發言者我哋都歡迎你嚟，但只能夠有三分鐘，好嘛？希望三分鐘完成你哋嘅發言。多謝大家，好，繼續。I would like to invite Miss Allen to speak.
Good afternoon. My name is Julie Allen and I'm the manager of Christian Action's Chung King Mansions Service Centre. Christian Action has been working with refugees here in Hong Kong for almost 30 years, first serving this population when there were waves of Vietnamese refugees fleeing to Hong Kong in the 1980s, and now at our centre in Chung King Mansions, where we've operated since.
2004，提供人道援助。我們也是個團體成員。我們榮幸今天能在此分享我們的經驗和建議，關於如何改善流離失所者、受酷刑申訴人和申請庇護者的狀況，我們現在稱為保護申訴人。在香港，我們的訊息很明確。在這個富裕的城市，
保護申請人正掙扎求生，他們需要更多政府幫助。保護申請人，被迫離開他們的國家而無法返回，通常來到這裡時，只帶著身上的衣服。他們必須在陌生的城市中，在壓力下航行，他們毫無地位或甚至無地位。
政府可以做更多。人權必須被尊重，而他們尋求保護和等待 resettlement。保護申請者必須獲得足夠的協助，以獲得在香港的尊貴居留。
一 dignified stay means that they have enough to eat and the personal freedom to choose their own food, that they live in a place that is affordable, habitable and safe, that they can access education and training opportunities while awaiting resettlement. These are simple things that many of us in this room take for granted, but they cannot.
政府的立場，就係關於福利服務到呢個羣眾，係要阻止一個人成為 destitute，而唔係創造一個磁效應。這就等於對我們而言，係指這些服務，這些服務是可得的，是簡直就係不足夠的。正如我們在基督教行動中所見，幾乎每天，很多保護申請人喺香港度過著他們嘅生活，被放棄。
在razor's edge， between destitute and not destitute， their physical needs for food， clothing and shelter are only just being met， and oftentimes tipping over to the edge.
讓我快速地address兩項關鍵福利問題。政府是more than aware that food assistance is in kind at a value of a thousand per month。 many clients here today and community members here today report that the amount of food is insufficient。 indeed, seventy percent of respondents in a recent survey conducted by the Refugee Concern.
Network， indicated that they simply do not receive enough food.
我們 propose that the government consider using vouchers or cash disbursements for this programme. Last week, we asked a group of recognised refugees to collect one of their monthly food bags valued at $333, create an itemised list of the foods that they collected, and then go out into the markets to go shopping.
基本上。
他們能購買那同一樣物品，只需229美元，節省104美元。在這個過程中，一張券或現金轉移系統將在長遠上節省政府的錢，並為受保人提供個人選擇食物，這既簡單又至關重要，以維持尊嚴。
Thank you.
Yes, we would like to invite Mrs. Miss Patricia N. Ho to speak. So.
Thank you. I'm one of the lawyers from Dalyan Associates, and we are a firm that has been representing this particular groups of persons for many years, many on a pro bono basis. And when it comes to the issue of welfare matters, we have been doing many pro bono work mainly because of the need. Now
I would just like to highlight. I've already submitted a paper, and I would like to highlight one thing that I find rather surprising. In my paper, I've quoted the government's statement in 2006, in July, seven years ago, and they talked about their policy when it comes to welfare, and they say this that they aim to provide support
which is considered sufficient to prevent destitution, while at the same time not creating a magnet effect for people to come to Hong Kong.
I just read the government's paper submitted this month, and in paragraph four, they basically stated the exact same sentence. I find that rather alarming to see the exact type of statements made by policymakers who have been dealing with the same problem all these years and have not changed the position in any way. Now, if I look to the key central
element or central point of this statement, they are using welfare as a deterrent effect to not basically to dispel people from coming to Hong Kong. This is not acceptable. We really need to basically scrutinise what the government is doing with with their money.
We have heard in the last month some figures from the government saying how much money they are spending on welfare, etc. I would invite I think the legislators to ask them for a breakdown. How much of that money is actually spent on legal advice where they are getting to ensure that they are providing the minimum possible.
welfare to people or minimum possible legal assistance and all the other things to people. It may be, I suspect, that the legal money that they're spending on money on legal advice will surpass the money that they're actually providing in substance to clients. I'd ask for serious scrutiny there.
我亦都想指出，政府有説過很多種的服務，為難民提供，但最後，這些服務都無法與
What we have seen today and statements from asylum seekers and persons of concerns. So I'd like to ask for serious scrutiny of these statements, and really not just to allow them to say whatever they wish.
嗯。
The government has been taking the position where they will continue to apply these basic, unlawful.
wanting policies until.
Some lawyers, like our own firm, take a case to sue them and win. Now we have one for many years, but takes years to bring these cases. It takes years to actually have the next win. And I would like to urge every legislator here to urge the government to actually run policies that are sensible and not wait for them to lose in another legal battle.
係。
Thank you, thanks.
我會嚟到邀請牧師佟利瑞嚟講。牧師
Thank you for allowing me to speak. I'm a pastor at the Vine Church in Wan Chai and.
Through the church, we have been providing food, financial aid, assistance and fellowship to over 250 refugees, torture claimants and asylum seekers on a regular basis. Through our community arm, the Vine Community Services, our written contribution has been submitted together with Hong Kong refugee.
庇護協會、維心社、基督教行動、避難者關懷網絡和人權國際。
Many have spoken today about human rights, and the protection claimants themselves have drawn attention to the deficits that they feel in the services offered to them.
我們也聽到關於法律義務， incumbent upon the administration to maintain adequate welfare。
嗯。
The protection claimants really have shown that this protection does not, in practice, exist.
但今天，作為 minister of the gospel，我 want to highlight the moral obligation upon the administration as a protection provider towards this vulnerable community.
The Bible makes it quite quite clear that we have a a moral duty to take care of those who are in the worse a worse situation than ourselves.
箴言章三 says， do not withhold good from those to whom it is due， when it is in your power to do it。
The Pharisees were also chastised by Jesus for their policy, which pursued legal correctness, but which at the same time was morally bankrupt.
It's quite clear that the administration's welfare policy set out in paragraph four of its policy paper.
是設計由保安局來滿足其自身保安政策，而唔係保護申請人的需要。
And it has been imposed on the social welfare department to implement as best they are able.
The policy, in short, is designed to allow any inconvenience, inhumanity, degradation, indignity and suffering, to protection claimants, short of actual destitution.
它係設計嚟送一個訊息畀任何潛在的申請庇護者，唔好嚟呢度，你係孤單嘅。
the policy implies that we, as the Hong Kong administration and civil society, are willing to sacrifice mental health, livelihood and the well-being of 5,000 or so protection claimants.
所以，七百萬 of us 居民 can 絆 on to our wealth and avoid our moral duty to help those that we have an obligation to protect and provide for.
我們cannot justify the suffering of a few of the weakest in order to protect the benefits of the majority.
我們 reject 這政策，作為被道德上出位。
任何改善到福利政策的claimants， must start by changing this morally bankrupt policy， because it cannot form the basis of any just welfare provision， and I urge the administration not to tinker with the present policy。 We need to develop a policy。
policy that respects the rights of the recipients and reflects the reputation of Hong Kong in the developed world for justice and fairness. Thank you. Thank you.
誒，連安妮小姐。
Thank you. Welfare assistance and right to work both concern whether a person is able to sustain his own living, and I like to take this opportunity today to focus a bit on the right to to work.
And most of the clients that we know, they all would like to work. Most of them have been working in their countries and and able-bodied persons who would like to contribute to society and be self-reliant.
但係，right now，the policy from the government is that they are not allowed to work，and this really does lead to many problems。We've seen families who have been torn apart，or there are lots of family problems in，especially。
We've seen.
with the males that who used to work in their home countries, that when they're not able to work or support their own family, that they do break down or get have mental health problems. So we do have some clients who
have to be on medication or receive counselling.
所以，definitely，allowing，people，to，work，would，be，beneficial，for，their，mental，health，and，also，for，their，families.，And，I，think，the，government，should，take，a，look，at，other，countries.
because for instance in Australia, if you're an asylum seeker, after six months you are allowed to work, even though you're not recognised as a refugee. And the same with UK, it's after 12 months in US 150 days, and New Zealand takes special consideration for.
所以，如果係一個家庭，他們可能會得到一個工作許可證。
第二樣嘢，我好想聚焦喺職業培訓。
嗯。
We have had over the years lots of clients who were.
青少年或在早期20s，both refugee and asylum seekers，who were quite young，and but they they couldn't attend secondary school or primary school in Hong Kong because they they were more than 18.
And their background was that maybe they they came from Somalia and they had five years of education because of the war.
或，甚至更少。
and we help them apply for vocational training at the vocational training council.
但係，都都rejected。
and，the vocational training council's policy，is that。
職業訓練是 for preparation for local employment，所以，since they don't have a right to work in Hong Kong， they could not attend this these kind of courses， so they actually were left with nothing.
They were maybe 18, 19 years old, but they, I mean, they don't have a right to work, and they couldn't attend any kind of training or education. So they were just left there stranded.
嗯，thank you.
所以， our recommendation is that the government should.
Of course, allow asylum seekers and refugees to work after some time, and then also.
focus on the you especially with the youth on vocational training. Thank you.
哦，Thank you.
我會 like to um invite Mr. speak, Mr. Peter to speak, Mr. Peter.
Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
I am Peter, technician mechanic auto.
機械。
嗯。
我有學士學位喺機械。
所以，我有我 own shop back home。
但係，當我有問題，政府。
my shop was destroyed, and I came to Hong Kong.
我 stay eight years no one come without working.
all because of the government does not want.
to give us a chance to prove that we are useless.
啊！
and help.
ourselves.
many among the seven thousand asylum seeker refugee have degree.
have a qualification.
要畀用於社會。
但政府， of Hong Kong does not give us that chance.
Giving.
一 chance to a refugee and a stream seeker.
will not harm Hong Kong government.
但，contrary， it will help and contribute something good for the society.
我 want to finish this to say there's a saying saying that.
給一 fish  to a man.
and we eat for one day.
and come back to you and beg for more.
That's what ISIS is doing. Give us fish.
It's not enough. We have to come and beg for, and beg them for more.
教一 man， how to fish。
And we.
會幫會幫呃幫。
to himself, feed himself.
feed the community.
and contribute to the society.
所以，我們需要。
The government to help us.
to give us a chance to prove.
ourself。
for them to know that we are not useless.
A lot of people.
In this阿斯蘭斯卡和土耳其，claim， we have ability。
We have knowledge, we have worked before, but right now it's like we are useless.
We are nothing.
但 if。
Hong Kong government can give us a chance to prove ourselves. They will know that we are useful for society.
some of them, some of of us need training as well. For example, our technician, eighty years then won't come. I'm not doing anything.
但係，如果我 have to go to another country，我 need to wear。
所以我有，我我需要另一training，所以我會ask香港政府to consider that。Thank you。Thank you。
我會像要邀請Mr. Philip Calori講話。Mr. Calori。
Thank you very much for giving us this opportunity. My name is Karani, Philip Karani. The
The head of the UNHCR office in Hong Kong.
UNHCR，The United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees。
是。
Given mandated by the international community by the United Nations to coordinate international protection.
Action for the wildlife protection and resolution of refugee problems. So that explains our presence here.
啊！
UNHCR's presence in Hong Kong dates back to the 1950s.
UNICEF first came to Hong Kong soon after the organisation was established in 1951.
and the reason UNHCR came to Hong Kong was to advocate.
for ways in which refugees coming to Hong Kong, mainly from Mainland China, that time, could be given assistance.
This is important because our role and presence in Hong Kong dates back to a time when Hong Kong itself, most of the people in Hong Kong today, were in need of international assistance.
We have over the last 30 or so years had a permanent presence in Hong Kong.
and our efforts have revolved around.
倡議和提供援助給申請庇護者和難民在香港。
In terms of today's deliberations, we've made a written submission.
This submission is based on interviews and discussions that we held with refugees in various forums.
Many of the issues we identified have in fact been presented here this afternoon. We've listened to the protection claimants who have come out in very compelling ways to explain the situation as they face it in Hong Kong.
and to recap, many of these issues revolve around accommodation. We've heard that accommodation allowance provided through the assistance programme is insufficient and does not allow refugees to find safe and adequate housing.
linked to this, of course.
是 also the issue of a payment of utility expenses.
and of course the issue of renter deposits. These are issues that have been identified here, and we would like to urge the government to review the levels of assistance given for accommodation.
We've also had presentations about food assistance.
Various issues have been brought up regarding food assistance, and we would like to urge the government to look at that again carefully, to see whether in fact there could be a re-examination and possibly consider a system of a voucher system as opposed to the current system where either because of a
Thank you.
This is not quite working. So very briefly, our submission covers many of these points, and I'm glad that many have in fact been highlighted by the.
Thank you, Mr. Clemence himself. Thank you very much.
我哋會想請Professor Simon Young講。Professor Young。
Thank you very much for the invitation. The Centre for Comparative and Public Law, the Faculty of Law, Hong Kong U, makes essentially one main submission, and that is that we recommend the government to carry out a comprehensive and comparative study of the standards of.
社會和經濟 protections for asylum seekers in other countries, and I think there's been reference to this in one of the earlier presentations, but we essentially say that there's three good reasons why this study should be carried out. The first
We need to know if what is happening now in Hong Kong falls below international standards, and I think clearly from what we've heard already, there's very good reasons to think that it does. And I think a study like this would tell us just to what extent it does fall below such standards. The second reason, of course.
是，那它可激發新想法和新方式的可能服務。為甚麼在香港，我們只有一個服務供應商，一個與ISS的合約？為甚麼沒有其他替代的服務方式？我們聽過一些標準。
Common law countries, which are very decent, but very recently, not too far from here, in Malaysia. And Malaysia is very interesting because in Malaysia, they are like Hong Kong. They're not a party to the Refugee Convention. Yet, very recently, they've said that they've decided to allow refugees and asylum seekers.
to work, not just only to work, but also to train them as well, because they've seen that as a matter of good policy, this is the way to go, and I would commend those developments to this government.
Furthermore, and the third reason is of course that such a study would help to promote more proactive policymaking. Right? We shouldn't have to wait for the courts to tell us what to do. And there will probably be more cases going to the courts if we just sit back and do nothing. We could keep repeating what was written.
八年前，它會just come back and haunt the government when it gets to the courts. And by that time, it could well be too late. People, asylum seekers, could be returned to face torture because they felt that they they're living in destitute situations in Hong Kong. And in fact, to to effect have that effect would be in violation
of the basic principle of non-refoulement. Thank you very much.
哦，Thank you. Next.
Now, would like to invite Ms. Das to speak, Ms. Das. Thank you very much for this opportunity. I've been a researcher and a clinical counsellor in this community for the past three years, and I believe this is an opportunity today to begin to work together and open dialogue around the holistic needs of refugee.
難民、申請者和受虐聲請人。
作為這社區進入我們的海岸，很多他們是 traumatized。It is critical we promote protective factors at the macro, meso and micro levels of society, such as social support, resources, access to fundamental services.
Today, I focus on health and mental health as a crucial aspect.
我哋想開始由認可這社區嘅無數強項。喺呢個破碎嘅系統喺香港，佢哋嘅韌性係每日測試。
但 even the most resilient people can be broken, and unfortunately, in my experience, working with this community, I've seen high rates of depression, post-traumatic stress, anxiety, as well as violence, family violence, substance use, and unfortunately, suicidal ideation.
As we open this valuable dialogue on how to improve the current system, I urge the Hong Kong government to focus on general health and psychosocial support as a key element.
training of healthcare providers, local clinical social workers, mental health counsellors, psychologists and psychiatrists is imperative.
這是因為在這個社區，我們在處理特殊 needs。
for example, many of these people have gone through torture, complex trauma, complicated grief, loss of family, home, and just imagine not even knowing whether your family is still alive.
作為這社區經由庇護和折磨系統篩選，它是最關心他們獲得接觸精神和行為服務，以預防再 traumatization。
我echo the voices here advocating for researching best global practices. I believe at this juncture there is an opportunity to promote a holistic intervention model for this community. I also emphasise the need for collaboration within the communities, interdisciplinary advocacy amongst service providers and tailored, culturally appropriate and inclusive service.
For individuals and communities, for individuals, the level of needed support will vary. Assessing and treating trauma is crucial, as is promoting strengths and resilience. Drawing upon a holistic approach to enable social support for refugees, asylum seekers and torture claimants could prove to be an effective strategy. Thank you very much.
thank you，多謝所有人今日畀意見。嗰同事如果有難題同大家商量，我手上總共有七個同事要發言，而我會一定要四點半秘書處話聽，我要交場。咁咧我就想同大家講，我第一個想畫線，就算畫線之後我處理唔到，因為張超龍仲有議案，我仲處理議案，比。
書處提議，我必須要四點半完成曬，因為下邊個會嚟緊，個會同樣福利加民政一齊嘅，噉啊想聽大家同事意見。如果我呢個時候第一個劃線，第二個兩個每人有兩分鐘，我尚且要畀翻三分鐘，政府先回應翻團體講嘢，聽大家同唔同意？
我諗你要，我哋點都會一定喺個時間內做曬所有嘢嘛？係劉華興，唔該，係你個會嘅。不過我可唔可以建議你開多個會咧？你人哋咁多人嚟講嘢，你匆匆咁去處理咗又唔係幾好啦。噉你咪會後再開多個會咯，主席。如果呢個會後咧，就因為由於我哋跟住嗰個就福利同民政。唔係今日。
呀！真。
嗱，咁咧我我都聽同事其他意見啦。如果擲日咧，我哋呢次揾時間都好辛苦，先揾到嚿時間出嚟。好，阿郭明亨。
誒，我都係跟開呢樣嘢好耐，因為咧呢啲團體咧，佢哋真係等咗好耐先有依個機會嚟講嗰幾分鐘。明白嘅。如果你叫官員回應三分鐘，我哋回應兩分鐘，有咩意思就冇意思嘅。因為郭榮亨，我想強調，立法會經常就面對種痛苦嘅局面。我做福利，經常都處理住呢啲痛苦，不過。
咧，我願意再諗個時間。不過，我想話畀大家聽，今日度呢個會期度得我哋好辛苦嘅。噉我諗張超紅或者個副主席冇嚟，佢都知我哋過程。但點都咧，我係尊重大家嘅。如果大家話集日再去討論，我同意。不過，我就想嗱，而家已經係答議嘅啦。噉啊，張超紅嗰個咧就未做嘅議案嘅。如果噉樣就張超紅。
拼埋所有同事問問題，我另外開個會。我就希望由政府應翻，因為今日除咗個個團體、誒個人，包括係呢個難民公署、香港大學啲等等都嚟講嘅，我都希望政府有個完整啲回應。所以我就想大家同唔同意我呢個處理？如果同意咧，就話我哋請政府係。
回應咗之後，再。
另外一個會好嘛，張朝元。
噉樣，我同意開多個會，個即係開多次會，我哋當然係即係同意同埋覺得應該啦，因為呢件事誒需要更加多時間同埋仔細啲去討論。但係我唔想今日咁多團體嚟到咧，我哋就好似冇一啲咁多成果。
我擠喺大家枱面嘅動議咧，其實係一個好基本嘅一種嘅睇法。咁如果主席同埋我哋同事容許嘅話咧，如果可以處理咗我動議咧，就至少我希望團體咧覺得今日翻去咧。
都睇到呢個嘅事務委員會有一個基本嘅立場，亦都就住呢點咧，政府可以作個下一次開會嘅時候，我明白你意見。習慣上我哋談中議。
今日喺咁短時間咧處理唔到張志雄議員所提出嚟嗰個嘅議案嘅嚇，因為大家冇時間去討論，噉你又即刻匆匆話要即刻去去支持或者唔支持個議案，咁點可以做得到咧？係咪？不過主要我都提醒下你，因為咧誒跟住嚟好多同事咧係可能放假，咁呢度咧好多唔係福利。
委員會嘅，你到時咧，福利委員會咧，你揾到時間揾唔到人，噉我覺得咧都要留意下呢樣嘢嘅。誒，多謝。你撐係撐唔到，因為你除非開啲誒其他嘅會。嗱，我我我先講咧，我即係再講誒同同事講，我哋度呢個時間同秘書處，包括埋跟住嚟嘅馬逢國同埋阿阿張國柱。
度咗好耐，即係點都好，我就覺得嗱，我我就想噉樣。
公道啲，咁多團體嚟。
誒，我真係好希望政府詳細啲回應翻大家。即係而家大家即係個個難處都問你香港政府到底點啊嘛。咁所以我就想話餘下嘅時間，我就唔想處理其他嘢，就由政府去答喺答個人當中。如果有某啲同事要同政府去開課或者點咧，我就覺得喺嗰度作一個處理就好嘛。
總之，我就十誒四點半一定準時交場，噉就處理唔到。張超，我講嘛，長毛，你仲有冇其他好嘅意見咧？得議，唔使講啦，人哋畀佢哋講好過啦。O K，咁仲好添嗱。如果大家都認為噉，我覺得最好處理。我多謝阿長毛嗱。咁而家開始啊嘛，我另日再討論，包括埋張超個個，好嘛？
誒希望到時揾時間嘅時候咧，大家都能夠睇點辦法去大家一齊去栽埋一個會啊嘛！好多謝。就我我希望睇局誒保安局或者搭搭啊，或者福利啊物體，你都要搭嘅，好嘛？兩邊咧都係搭冇太多啦，但係搭呢個係誒五分鐘到，之後我畀翻團體再問翻你大家啊嘛。
兩個局裏邊都答我話，OK唔該。
多謝主席，我盡量簡短啦。誒，今日都十分感謝嚇所有團體嚟到，特別係有人延伸説法噉樣畀咗啲意見我哋。其實經過最近一連串即係社會或者係即係喺議會嘅討論咧，我哋都誒留意到咧，就現行嗰個計劃係無論喺運作上或者係喺嗰個各方面。
支援嘅水平方面咧，可能都係有一啲地方咧，係需要改善嘅。
噉我哋咧今日翻去咧會細心考慮所有團體議員畀到我哋嘅意見。噉我哋係會即係逐項逐項去睇咧，睇下有啲咩地方係可以短期嘅，或者係喺誒長啲嘅時間咧係可以作出改善。咁實際上咧呢方面誒社會福利署咧已經係開始咗一啲嘅工作係做緊嘅。
咁誒，我哋個政策目標其實即係剛才有一啲團體亦都提出過，認為我哋應該係即係誒再考慮噉樣。噉我哋其實個原則都係清晰嘅，即係無論任何一個喺外國嚟到，即係非法入境又好，逾期居留又好，如果佢係提出個申請咧，我哋係其實目標係。
盡快希望可以處理到嗰個申請完結咗。如果佢係確立嘅，我哋等佢喺香港可以獲得一個免遣返嘅保障。如果唔確立嘅，我哋盡快希望可以將佢遣送離開香港。
咁誒嗰個現時呢個安排嘅背景咧，就係當呢一誒班人士喺香港逗留嘅期間咧，佢的而且確衣食住行其他各方面嘅生活係有需要。
噉我哋的而且確係為咗避免咧，誒呢一班嘅人喺香港咧係陷入困境咧，所以係由零六年開始咧係有呢一個嘅安排。
誒目前咧就誒工作方面咧，其實誒如果係已經確立咗申請嘅一啲申請人，佢誒如果向入境處提出咧，入境處處長其實係有酌情可以批准佢哋咧喺香港工作嘅。
咁呢個咧就唔包括係誒等待嘅申請人，因為誒相信大家都理解咧誒乜嘢人可以喺香港工作咧係一個十分之敏感嘅問題嚇，咁所以咧即係呢個唔係淨係從當事人角度嚟睇，我哋都睇咧香港即係整體嘅一個利益去考慮。
咁誒，剛才有提有團隊提到咧，係關於譬如話誒平邪或者一啲個案嘅處理咧，我想交畀誒副處長咧係去解釋一下我哋跟進嘅工作係進行成點。麥太嚇，多謝主席，多謝咁多位即係正話畀嗰個意見。誒，正如我同事所講咧，即係誒現有嗰個人道立場。
嗰個即係援助咧，由零六年一路延續到現在啦。我哋都睇到係有一啲地方，我哋可以改善嘅。咁即係聽到大家嘅意見啦，我哋喺日後再提供個服務嘅時候咧，我哋都會作一個參考。咁至於平斜嗰個情況嘅時候咧，就喺嗰個即係租住地方咧，其實喺平斜租住嘅。
朋友咧，大部分喺佢哋未向I.S.S.申請個援助之前咧，就已經係喺嗰度居住嘅。即係有部分嘅朋友可能係覺得個居住嘅環境係唔理想嘅。咁呢呢方面咧，我哋都係即係得到I.S.S.同事嗰個嘅合作啦。如果個別嘅個案係真係覺得有需要揾另外嘅地，
方嘅時候咧，國際社嗰邊嘅同事咧係樂意為佢哋提供協助嘅。咁而正話提到嗰個即係租金緩助嗰度咧，就開始我哋零六年提供呢個緩助，到現在啦，我哋中間係有作過一個調整。咁另外我哋依家亦都參考翻即係市場嗰個租金嘅趨勢啦，就
亦都係檢視緊嗰一個嘅租金水平嘅，咁呢個咧我哋都睇到係有一個即係改善嘅空間喺度。咁但係詳細嘅情況咧，我哋都希望喺嚟緊呢一兩個月咧，係可以有一個嘅定案，究竟上調係點咧？咁咁雖然咧，即係正話不同嘅團體都有提到千二蚊呢一個數字，呢個基本。
上面咧係一個參考嘅數字，喺個別嘅個案，若果係真係有特殊嘅情況嘅時候咧，佢哋係可以向國際社嗰邊咧提出佢嗰個個案嘅情況，咁國際社亦都會因應翻個別嘅情形啦，係去作出一個嘅即係調教嗰方面嘅工作嘅。咁而即係最近報章。
亦都有即係報道，有個別嘅即係租約咧，所列在嘅地址咧，係同實際上住嘅地址係有不同嘅。咁呢個我哋即係收咗呢啲詳細資料之後啦，我哋都請咗ISS咧係要作出一個詳細嘅調查，然後再向我哋作翻一個報告。咁若果有
真係一啲違法嘅情況嘅時候咧，我哋都唔排除，我哋都會有一啲採取一啲法律性嘅行動。譬如如果有一啲詐騙嘅情況或者點樣樣啊噉，噉我估即係喺嗰個即係援助方面嘅時候咧，正話即係阿歐生都有提到，我哋都要攞一個嘅平衡，點樣喺避免即係受助人。
係唔係陷於困境之餘咧？我哋亦都要整體去睇翻嗰個援助嗰個可持續性，同埋即係唔希望會引嚟一個即係持續嘅效應。咁喺呢度咧，即係我估基本嘅原則，即係我哋都要守翻。但係喺嗰個提供嘅細節裡面咧，我哋都同意係可以有。
啲嘅地方喺聽咗大家意見之後咧，我哋喺日後嗰個即係嘅協議同即係一啲服務團體提供服務嘅時候咧，我哋都可以即係作一個嘅參照啊！多謝主席。OK，誒，今日我哋嘅人客有啲都係團體嚟嘅，包括國際社，我諗或者你哋都畀一啲意見啊，即係剛。
才兩位官員咁答就話，誒福利處阿麥太就話，大概兩個月度會檢討啲相關嘅事，但係啲嘢佢提咗出，確實誒服務社，我睇有冇其他團體想問一問咧？透過你哋好嘛？
冇啊嘛，OK，我哋同事有冇嘢想要係係？阿劉興宇唔該，係阿主席啊！我相信團體提出有啲係好迫切嘅問題嚟㗎，噉就係包括住屋嘅地方啦，啊，你話CNN都話到我哋係地獄嘅噉樣，同埋食物唔足夠，同埋。
買啲細路仔冇得去讀書，即係其實咧一咧，我希望我哋第日可以有個團咧去睇一睇嗰啲地方嘅主席。但係幾位官員可唔可以講咧？喺呢頭先講嘅幾樣嘢咧，喺呢一兩個禮拜內咧係可以馬上處理到，即係揾翻一啲可以符合人去住嘅地方畀佢住。
同埋咧，佢話唔夠食物啊！嗰啲係咪畀到佢？同埋電視又話有啲細路仔六歲五歲就冇得讀書啦，因為你哋摟咗佢個條件。呢啲嘢係咪可以處理到咧？主席噉，如果就算開唔到會咧，我希望好快九月翻嚟，係盡快開會，就叫啲官員嚟答曬佢。咁其實喺呢個期間，啲團體可以話畀我。
嚟聽㗎個哦，原來一滴嘢都冇做過㗎啊！食又唔夠食，又繼續瞓豬欄啊！噉樣我真係多得嚟唔少啊！香港嘅聲名譽啊，掃曬地噉係咪呢幾樣啊？啲細路仔一定要有書讀，係咪可以答到啊？係阿胡生頭先乜睇？
我先講誒嗱，居住方面咧，其實阿麥太剛才都有提到誒，一直以嚟咧，其實喺平斜地區嗰誒誒居住嘅一班呢一班嘅受助人咧，假如佢哋認為係希望搬離開嗰個地方咧，其實佢哋係可以主動向服務社提出嘅。服務社每一個月咧。
會同佢哋會面每一次咧，誒，其實佢哋都有機會可以提出，就係可唔可以協助咧，係幫忙佢哋去搬去一個比較或者佢哋認為誒比較適合嘅地方。咁喺呢方面咧，誒誒服務社係會繼續跟進嘅。呢一個機會咧亦都係繼續存在。咁誒呢個機制其實亦都係喺每一個受
救助人嘅個案裏邊咧，都係噉樣安排嘅。咁誒。
讀書方面咧，誒呢個就係由教育局去安排啦。咁誒喺香港嘅誒停留嘅呢一班嘅申請人，佢哋有一啲咧喺誒佢一啲係帶埋啲小朋友嚟到香港啦。噉佢有一啲咧就喺香港等候嘅期間咧，就有下一代啦。
咁無論如何咧，佢係適齡誒入學嘅一啲嘅申請人嘅下一代。如果佢哋係向誒教育局提出係希望咧安排入學咧，誒程序上咧，教育局係會向入境處咧係作出一個查詢。咁查詢咧係誒就一個方面查詢嘅啫，就係到底呢一個。
誒誒申請人或者佢嘅下一代會唔會喺短期之內係誒可能佢譬如話個個誒申請已經完成咗啦，咁咧佢係不確立嘅，噉佢係會被遣送離開。
假如唔係嘅，即係話，假如呢一個嘅誒小朋友佢喺香港咧係會停留一段比較長嘅時間咧，咁入境處係會回覆翻教育局咧，就係誒嗰個誒佢唔會短期內被誒遣送離開啦。咁教育局咧就再按佢嘅一個即係入學嘅程序咧去處理，即係誒安排。
到底係咪有學位啊？諸如此類噉樣，咁所以咧，基本上我哋誒嗰個嘅誒，即係大體嚟講，嗰個安排係噉樣。咁至於即係傳媒有報道嗰啲嘅個案咧，我哋需要多少時間再去理解一下嚇。咁食物方面或者我或者等間先回應好嘛？誒，我而家有三個同事舉手，咁而家仲係誒呢個。
二十分，我哋仲有十零分鐘。我希望每人兩分鐘，三位咧就係誒。
好你，我有個團體埋，O.K.，好啊。
講埋食物啦嘛～
好嗯。
好啦。
聽唔到啊！主席，你對埋啲個麥嚇，唔該。
按檢討嘅時候咧，其實都會有一個即係表格咧，係畀個申請人咧係去tick佢需要嗰個食物嘅。咁如果食物嘅種類咧，其實亦都係不斷去因應翻嗰個需要而作出一個添加。咁而個量方面咧，就應該係一個普通成年係嘅量，或者個小朋友嘅量咧係。
應該滿足到嘅。若果話發覺有唔滿足到嘅情況咧，呢啲個別個案咧，我哋都希望詳細啲瞭解下個情況係點解會有咁情形出現。因為嗰個數量同個即係款式咧，亦都係盡量滿足即係嗰個申請人嗰個需要，包括佢喺嗰個即係宗教啊、種族各方面嗰小朋。
有嘅時候，亦都係有小朋友嘅奶粉啊、食物啊嗰啲係提交嘅。咁至於正話，亦都有即係朋友表示過嗰個攞食物嘅次數嘅多少咧。其實呢個係可以作出一個嘅適應或者調教嘅。有啲嘅家庭，若果佢一次過係攞太多嘅時候咧，我哋都理解到可能個次。
數係比較頻密一啲咧，就會係比較方便啲。咁呢個咧就國際社嘅同事喺同我哋作出個協議嘅時候咧，都可以就住呢一方面係作出一個嘅調教。有啲嘅申請人可能佢唔想去得咁頻密嘅，噉佢嗰個攞嘅次數咧，可能相對係會比較多一啲。噉我估呢個即係我哋。
冇一個定案，一定話佢一個月要嚟六次定係幾多次。好多時都真係因應翻佢嗰個嘅情況。咁亦都有朋友有提過，就話我去攞食物嘅時候拎住太多，我搭公共車可能係唔方便。特別一啲家庭可能係牽涉到婦女帶住小朋友嘅。如果有呢啲咁情況嘅時候咧，其實依家個安
安排咧就國際社都會酌情咧係因應佢嗰個情況，有陣時都係提供一個的士費用畀佢哋。咁有陣時可能係如果有兩家人住埋一齊，亦都同一日去攞呢個食物嘅時候咧，可能佢哋係會一齊去分擔一個的士嘅費用，呢個都會有。噉我估呢個亦都希望大家明白咧，有陣時我哋喺使用。
公堂嘅時候咧，我都要睇一睇翻嗰個嘅用途嗰方面。噉我估我簡單講住咁多先。多謝主席。好，跟住咧就，誒好。
Have a quick feedback to some of the statements made. I think one of the biggest disappointments I'm having is that, Montlozier, the many of the responses given are basically maintaining that your current system is adequate. The fact is that it's not. You say that you know certain you are providing
adequate food. The fact is, the whole population doesn't think that there's enough. It's not有夠畀聽唔夠。The whole population thinks that it's not. The other thing is about rental. You say that most one one two hundred is only basic, and that some people will be topped up. The fact is, you only get a top up if you get a valid medical certificate.
説，你有骨折、骨折、腿或什麼，非常非常少人有超過一千兩百。我只，也想説，有個建議，ISS會幫助人移動輪椅，如果需要，或如果人想要。再，我們知道系統如何運作。
ISS會 allow the person to go out there in society and find a place. And if they're able to find a place within 1,200, then they will allow and help them to move. But if they're not, the fact is they're gonna stay there. So if there's no practical options for people, not no practical help, ISS is not going to take these people by the hand.
and go offer them other places. That's simply not the case happening here. And the final, I just have one little concern: is they say that you know if some people have given false addresses, then they will consider taking legal action against them. That raises an alarm bell to me because these persons are vulnerable, and if any asylum seekers
係啊，係
回應兩句，誒一個咧就係誒剛才講話可以誒去揾國際社去尋求協助咧，佢其實都有兩方面，一個就係當然佢如果係揾到其他地方係佢認為適合搬嘅，咁可以向國際社去要求協助啦。但係其實最比較主要嘅咧係，譬如話呢一類個案，佢係畀。
必可以有能力係自己用自己嘅辦法去揾到嘅話咧，噉佢哋係可以向國際社尋求嗰個協助咧，就係要求國際社幫佢去揾一個係即係誒適合嘅地方去即係搬遷。咁呢個咧就唔係話要佢再趕佢出去自己去揾。咁另外咧就係剛才阿麥太提到嗰個嘅即係。
所以，如果我哋喺調查過程發現有一啲地方係需要再作出，譬如話係即係法律方面嘅跟進咧，係講緊如果個業主即係佢係提供一啲虛假嘅資料去畀誒服務社同埋社署係去即係關於嗰個租金津貼方面嘅一個安排。咁如果我哋有呢啲資料係。
見到嘅話咧，我係會即係轉交即係執法部門嚟跟進。噉係講緊業主方面。O K。
誒，我哋而家仲有五分鐘，誒四分鐘。我諗誒，每個人講分鐘啊嘛。我手上有三個誒舉隻手嘅，就何俊仁、黃碧雲同埋張超雄。就何俊仁一分鐘，誒李娟一分鐘。講完就冇得再答㗎啦，好嘛？O K。主席，我哋係香港人，個個有身份證，我哋個個知道千二蚊。
可以做到咩地方？香港真係講笑噉。正話副處長仲話誒坐的士啊，大家夾錢。喂，你寫明話明最平嘅交通費啊，要用點坐的士咧？我真係唔明白，所以你嘅諗你嘅心仲諗住硬坐的士，真係我覺得誒，真係你都知唔知道發生咩事咧噉樣咁咧就誒同埋咧誒，我想噉樣，因為冇時間講。
我想咧，第日你哋你哋政府嘅文件咧，話畀佢聽有幾多小朋友已經冇書讀嘅。我最緊張呢樣嘢，呢個第一樣嘢。第二樣嘢點解唔畀工作啊？係咯嗱，呢樣嘢我睇唔得到立，因為點解咧？就係你再用話好敏感畀佢哋工作，點解點解唔可以去去去做工作咧？對佢哋去申請難民。
或者酷刑公約嘅嘅嘅受害者身份，有咩嘢違背先？點解人哋第啲國家做到咧噉樣？噉我咧仲有一樣嘢，你記住咧，工作咧係可以對呢班咁即係喺香港滯留喺香港，即係幾幾困苦人嚟講咧，係有有啲有啲即係使佢唔好咁隔離，係咪啊？咁一反為如果你。
即係連工作都冇，要佢做義工咧，活喺咁貧困嘅環境之下咧，根本係極之不公義啊！清楚，張超紅。
誒主席。
誒，首先多謝咁多團體同埋啲難民自己上到嚟，佢哋其實係好勇敢㗎，因為好多誒喺香港，佢哋都擔心自己嘅安全問題啦。咁嚟到呢度，佢公開向大家咁講嘢咧，其實係一啲都唔容。
二。
我哋知道好多而家個生活咧，真係困苦。政府話唔會讓佢哋陷於困苦咧，呢個係大話嚟。因為頭先咧，即係Vision First嗰個嘅幻燈片都影得好清楚，可惜我哋啲燈光唔係安排得好好，睇得唔清楚。我自己去過好多次。
探過即係平斜啊、打鼓嶺一帶嘅難民，誒我都好贊成啊，劉慧卿議員，我哋呢個委員會咧可以安排一次誒去探訪一下，最好連埋嗰啲高官去探，等佢哋都落一次去睇下嗰啲乜嘢叫做困苦。
啊！我希望即係你盡快安頓。好唔該，跟住咧就黃碧雲。
都係主席。誒，我想就下一次會嘅時候咧，係誒政府答我哋幾個問題啦。第一，平均嗰個審核時間係幾長？嚇。
嗱點即係點點解唔可以縮短嚇？第二就係剛才都有人問，就係點解只係得一間機構就係呢個i i s s係負責呢個難民照顧咧咁噉，而似乎我哋擺落去嘅錢都唔少嘅，每年係二億噉，社署係負責監管呢啲錢係點使嘅噉，下一次上。
上嚟嘅時候，請你畀埋文件我哋。究竟呢一個ISS嗰二億嘅錢有幾多成係用喺行政費用？有幾多成係直接用喺難民嗰度？
第三個問題咧就關住嗰度啦，噉我哋咧其實有一啲空置嘅學校嘅。
有冇考慮過咧？係攞一啲空置嘅學校嚟係誒收容啊呢啲嘅誒難民？
嘅人士咧咁咁誒呢一個係咪會都去探討即係喺埋，因為我哋知道有啲校址校址啊冇用冇用到要諗辦法嚟做乜嘅。O.K.好多謝你，默默捐言。
主席，我記得我八年前喺一個嗯社福類機構工作嘅時候咧，誒其實有位代表都喺度嘅。當時我哋其中一個服務就係幫Asylum Seekers佢哋嘅福利。咁誒嗰陣時，我記得我係負責做media嘅，我哋要安排一啲嘅誒當事人出嚟做啲訪問，想講佢哋嘅遭遇咧，絕。
對唔容易，好難嘅，所以我覺得今日誒有關嘅同事，即係有關嘅當事人，即係佢哋啲protection claimant，佢哋肯走出嚟講你哋自己嘅感受，講你自己嘅遭遇咧，我覺得好重要，因為有你哋去講翻，畀我哋聽，你哋嘅知道，即係我我做過，所以我知。咁但係我覺得比較遺憾嘅就係我哋我嗰陣時。
剛係八年前去做誒嘅嘅，已經講緊我哋資源唔夠。我哋以為政府有啲噉嘅新嘅撥款嘅時候咧，可以解決到佢哋嘅問題，但係仍然都係解決唔到。講咗咁多年都係有呢個老問題，咁所以我覺得即係政府你真係唔該快啲做啲嘢。而且第二樣嘢咧，政啊主席後先講話，我哋會再開會，我覺得。
如果佢再開會咧，應該同埋保安事務委員會係一個join meeting，因為中間有一個好重要嘅問題，就係佢哋點樣去解決佢哋可以嗰個誒嗰個嗰個資格嗰個認證嗰個問題。今日嘅會咧係join meeting嚟嘅，所以我哋就係就到神父誒保安佢話佢哋唔參與，咁所以就由我嚟召開，唔緊要嗱我。
我哋啲又誒嗰位同事誒，我總結下，將今日所有嘅同事同埋有關團體意見咧，畀書主寫咗落嚟㗎啦。咁頭先個好清楚，我聽到物體就話：你畀兩三個禮拜我啦噉樣。咁跟住劉興健就問佢：你一兩月得唔得咧？我交份大翻嚟開會，我同意嘅，即係我諗，如果你即刻要去答會，可能答到我哋噉。
我就建議博索性係九月份嘅上旬，我哋同秘書處。我估計而家大家遲少少要走人嘅啦。噉啊，跟住有啲訪問團出，我立法會有訪問團出嘅。咁變咗噉嘅時候咧，如果大家都認為O K咧，我就同埋副主席再同埋保安再商量下。我哋大約九月嘅上旬睇下大家得唔得。如果大家話唔得咧，我哋會秘書處畀個。
大家填落翻嚟好唔好啊？OK，如果大家冇意見咧，嗯OK。又可以遲啲，但係我哋你話跟住再開會嘅嘛？我哋九月份得唔得嗰份？即係翻到九月先開會。嗱，剛才劉興噉嘅建議，我仲想問大家同唔同意？唔係，我仲以為我哋喺即係呢一個會期內開多次㗎。如果唔係，都算呢個。
會期內㗎，不過月份就唔係七月。七月我唔知，如果得我就唔使揾得咁慘啦，好嘛？唔係噉啊，早知處理咗我同意先冇啦，因為我我同啲同事講要討論先啦，冇拖多兩個月。嗰啲同事，我我特別相關嘅福利事委會，誒，因為今日呢個福利事委會會議嘅，我希望大家落。
攞翻時間出翻嚟好嘛？嗱，你哋話如果要八月份，我冇意見嘅八月或者九月份對呢個呢個嘅年度嘅會期，噉我就誒聽大家意見。今日就處理唔到問題啦。佢哋嘅主席已經馬逢國坐説嘅啦，噉我要讓翻位畀佢好嘛？OK，好。
我哋將我哋將兩件事都透過畀大家嘅一個填翻翻嚟表格啊嘛，睇下大家情況點。即係嗱，呢個就同同事講咗之後咧，都同政府講翻啦。剛才大家關心嘅教育啦、住啦，同埋一個噉嘅食嘅問題啦，以致工作問題咧，我希望物體好啦。
就係啊誒相關嘅保安局嘅同事咧，啊胡生都好啦，你盡快畀啲文件畀我哋立法會好嘛？好嘛？雖然我哋表面上放放暑假，實我哋冇放假嘅，你擺上畀我哋好嘛？OK，咁唔該曬大家，亦都多謝所有團體嚟，但唔好意思，由於而家係誒個會嘅時間。
間唔足夠討論多啲，噉啊點都多謝大家。我有任何嘅誒決定或者任何嘅信息，話翻畀大家聽。多謝大家。
O.K.好，馬逢國唔該。